Finding Aid for War of 1812 Collection
William L. Clements Library, University of Michigan
- War of 1812 collection
  - 1813 July 13. Ninian Pinkney ALS to Henry Dearborn; Niagara., 2 pages; Pinkney, a junior officer in the 5th regiment, provides a report on the regiment and recruiting new men; "I…will consider it a favour if you will permit me now or after the termination of the pending events…to attend to the Recruiting Service, or to report myself to the Secretary of War, as you may think most proper..."
  - 1813 July 15. Phineas Hammond ALS to Mrs. Phineas Hammond; Cantonment Burlington., 4 pages; News of what he has done in the army since he left home. He belongs to a force of 6,000 men; "I have good reason to suppose that an attack is meditated on the enemy by us, in considerable force (probably in Montreal) the issue is doubtful being untried, but I have little reason to doubt the end of a conflict of that kind, whose foundation is justice, and whose aim is peace. Yesterday we had one man shot for repeated desertion." Includes a memo by Margeret Porter from New Castle concerning Phineas Hammond.
  - 1813 July 17. Isaac Lyman ALS to Cyrus King; York, [Maine]., 2 pages; Disappointed by political leaders. "I have enough to do in silently deploring the miserable condition to which our Country is reduced by the weak and wicked policy of our Rulers. My own feelings on this subject I do not wish to impart to any one most especially to you, who need (I fear) a Physician of both mind and body in the City of pestilence war and desolation." Uncertain what the effects of recent bills may be, but notes the Federalist remembrance of "the prophet Jefferson's remark- that tax-gathers wou'd complete what useful labors did not." Believes Democracy is sickening and likely to fail, "and with it the host of Dependants who have so long consumed the peoples substance." Glad that the Senate has allowed Russell to stay home and hopes that [Daniel] Webster's (1782-1852) "resolutions will induce a development of tricks practiced by state jugglers." References "Southern war hawks" and hopes King will work towards peace.
  - 1813 July 18. Noah Morrison ALS to Hamilton McColester; Buffalo, [New York]., 3 pages; Account of local attack by British; "about three hundred of the British came acrost about three miles below Buffalo at Black Rock burnt the Barrick Spickt & carried away all the cannon…the Indians raised the Yell and commenced the fire So hot that the enemy were obliged to retrete in considerable of a hurry..." He lists his estimates of the casualties, includes postscript of a dangerous experience in Canada.
  - 1813 July 23. William Abney ALS to Jacob Vanlear; Augusta County, [Virginia]., 5 pages; Local news, British shipping, expecting an Indian attack.
  - 1813 July 24. Tho[ma]s B. Abercrombie ALS to W. Meredith; Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania]., 1 page; Recommending the wife and children of Walter Allison, who is a volunteer soldier, for aid; Meredith is part of a committee whose purpose is to assist the wives and children of volunteers under Col. Rush.
  - 1813 July 27. Amos Binney DS to Nathaniel Cushing., 1 page; Contract for the purchase of anchors for the Navy; "the said Nathaniel Cushing hath agreed…to furnish for the United States Navy Department and to deliver at the Navy Yard in Charlestown…the following number, sizes, & description of Anchors and at the prices herein named..." by March 1, 1814.
  - 1813 August 6. Decius Wadsworth ALS to John M. Taylor; Ordnance Department, Washington, [D.C.]., 1 page; Artillery and ammunition under order for the Northern Frontier.
  - 1813 August 8. Elizabeth Lee ALS to Mary L. Sparhawk; Templeton, [Massachusetts]., 1 page; News of her husband who is serving in the Navy; he had sailed for Cadiz, captured and sent to England; "I received letter from him a few days ago since the latest dated Liverpool 12th May, he was then in good health & expected soon to have his ship in possession..."
  - 1813 August 9 and 1813 August 16. Col. William A. Daingerfield, Brig. Gen. Young, et al., 2 pages; Recommendations for Thomas Monroe for military appointment; "[much] has been his moral character…that I…believe him worthy of an appointment in my [department] of the military service of the United States…"
  - 1813 August 11. John Black ALS to Pearl Spofford and Frederick Spofford; Goldsboro, [Maine?]., 1 page; Trade with Boston; he requests that barrels of pork and tobacco leaves be sent. Includes an ANS of Thos. Cobb requesting grass seeds.
  - 1813 August 13. [Pearl Spofford] [pseud] Peter Pinder ALS to Pearl Spofford and Frederick Spofford; St. John, [Maine]., 3 pages; Discusses trade in Canada, probably illicit, during the war; "pay good attention to our business as the times look (to me) very Black."
  - 1813 August 17. George Armistead ALS to Capt. Callender Irvin; Fort Niagara, New York., 2 pages; Concerning the theft of two horses, a nearby Native American tribe’s discontent, and a British mutiny; "A Mutiny was on foot in the british Garrison which has just been discover'd & repressed it was to have taken place this evening; there intention was to have murdered all the officers burnt the Garrison plundered & burnt West Niagara...they would have met with a warm reception from our cannon & muskets."
  - 1813 August 24. United States DS to Isaac White., 1 page; Receipt for $20, “for cap & clothes...in making my escape from upper Canada.”
  - 1813 September 1. A. S. Brooks ALS to Westport, Massachusetts Selectmen; Fort George., 1 page; Regarding land and pay left by the deceased Joseph Brownell; Brooks has his pay and after settling his accounts has money remaining and requests that any friends authorized to receive it to inform him. He had enlisted for 5 years and "is of course entitled to 100 acres of land."
  - 1813 September 2. Samuel G. Towne ALS to Pearl Spofford; St. Stephens, [Maine]., 3 pages; Concerning trade.
  - 1813 September 4. William Duane ANS to Callender Irvine; Adjutant General’s Office., 1 page; “I must decline doing what is proper and correct...”
  - 1813 September 5. Joseph W. Lawrence DS; Geneseo, [New York]., 2 pages; Orders for regiments in the 39th Brigade, including a list of the detachment of various captains, ensigns, lieutenants, and other soldiers from specific regiments. "The commandant of the 39th Brigade…confidently hopes and sincerely believes that the above orders will meet with promt and strict obedience."
  - 1813 September 7. Alexander Neef ALS to Andrew W. Bell; Burlington, [Vermont]., 2 pages; Description of a naval expedition and his naval force, with a list of ships and guns.
  - 1813 September 18. Nathaniel Z. Platt DS to Melancthon Woosley; Plattsburg, [New York]., 2 pages; Contract to build two store houses; "Platt of Plattsburgh arees to Build for the United States Two Storehouses of the following dimensions…" It is certified on verso by Woosley, dated January 5, 1814, who states "I conceive this Contract as fulfilled."
  - 1813 September 21. William Duane ANS; Adjutant General’s Office., 1 page; Regarding appointment of Lieutenant Bretton Evans, and officer in the 2nd Artillery.
  - 1813 September 23. James Madison LS to John Mason; Montpelier, [Orange, Virginia]., 4 pages; Regarding the harsh treatment of American prisoners of war at Halifax; "The encouragement which the Enimy seem to derive from our reluctance to retaliate their cruelty towards our military citizens in captivity, requires that an appeal should be made without delay, to their feelings for their own unfortunate people, as they have none for ours." He orders British prisoners to be placed under "a rigor of treatment" similar to those towards America prisoners.
  - 1813 September 24. Ferdinand L[eigh] Claiborne ALS to Lieutenant [James?] Bayley [Bailey?]; St. Ste[ph]ens, [Alabama]., 2 pages; Directions on gathering corn, pumpkins, and guarding their horses while at pasture at Col. [James] Caller’s (1758-1819) plantation."When your Horses are feeding in the field you must keep a pickett guard near them, in order to prevent straggleing parties of Indians from stealing them; and also a guard & sentinels a sufficient distance from the house to notify you of the approach of an enemy."Orders Bailey to retreat if they "hear of a body of Indians such as might probably jeopardize your horses." "There are circumstances that may occur, but are not calculated on; however in time of war and near an enemy a good soldier ought at all times be on his guard."Being sent to Coller’s in order to ready horses for battle, and advises Bailey to take good care of them and prevent any soldier from harming the property."Should any of your command be so lost to the honorable principles becoming a soldier, as to violate this order you will after dismounting him and taking from him his equipments, send him forward under guard with the charges and witnesses, to Mount Vernon to be tried by a court Martial."Includes an order for the Quarter Master to provide Bailey with a wagon for transport.
  - 1813 September 27. Jeremiah Lee, William Picket, and James Gray, Jr. DS to Charles Rich; Bridport, [Vermont]., 2 pages; Regarding arms, cartridges, and cannon lent by Charles Rich, a lieutenant colonel in the 3rd Regiment, 1st Brigade and 3rd division.
  - 1813 September 27. A. Shields DS to Charles Rich; Bridport, [Connecticut]., 2 pages; Regarding cannon and cartridges delivered to Charles Rich.
  - 1813 September 29. James Madison ALS to John Mason; Montpelier, [Orange, Virginia]., 1 page; Concerning the detention of seamen on British ships when war was declared; "The…detention of our Seamen who were on board British Ships when war was declared, will engage particular attention." He goes on to mention "the effect of their Testimony in proclaiming the cruelties they have suffered..."
  - 1813 September. Hosea Day Document; [Massachusetts]., 1 page; "Inspection and Muster Roll of Capt. Hosea Day." List of members.
  - 1813 October 5. William Duane ALS to Callender Irvine; Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania]., 3 pages; Concerning Army news, including efforts to protect the Delaware River and the duty and conduct of officers.
  - 1813 October 7. William Duane ALS to John M. Taylor; Adjutant General’s Office., 1 page; Issuing artillery; he orders 50 blank rounds and 50 rounds fixed ammunition to be allocated for each gun, and gives further orders regarding the movement of ammunition.
  - 1813 October 15. Daniel Rose ALS to Orchard Cook; Camp Chalaugay [Châteauguay, Quebec]., 1 page; Movement of army; "I inclose a sketch of the movements of this army from Burlington to this place, the tract of the army is marked with blue." Requests that Mr. [McClintock] see the sketch.
  - 1813 October 23. Bailey and Willis ALS to Daniel Sheldon, Jr.; New York., 4 pages; Discusses the running of the British blockade and gives instructions for Sheldon upon his arrival in Havana. Lists the prices of commodities, including coffee, brown sugar, and molasses.
  - 1813 October 24. A[ndrew] T. Goodrich ALS to Sarah M. Goodrich; New York., 3 pages; New York’s celebration of war victories; "I informed you before that the City Hall was to be lighted on the last evening in honor of our recent victories…" He mentions Tammany Hall, Washington Hall, and the American Museum. In front of City Hall were placed "representations of all the various naval actions that have taken place during the war..."; Original located in the Andrew T. Goodrich family correspondence.
  - 1813 October 28. John Monroe LS to David B. Mitchell; U.S. Department of State., 5 pages; Mitchell, the former governor of Georgia, has accepted Monroe's invitation to command forces attacking Creeks. Monroe describes the force and correspondence with the Governor of Tennessee [Willie Blount]. "The exposed situation of New Orleans, the probability that the enemy may make an attempt to take possession of it, and of other parts of that Country...increased by a knowledge that an expedition has been lately equipped from Halifax, necessarily draws our attention to that quarter."
  - 1813 November 9. Thomas Barcley Pr. DS; New York., 1 page; Regarding exchange of American prisoner James Cernon, "late mate of the American vessel St Augustin."
  - 1813 November 10. Robert Troup ALS to Abraham Van Vechten; Geneva, [New York]., 4 pages; Reports from Fort George and of Harrison and McClure preparing to attack Burlington. "Harison has only between 7 & 800 men with him - and they are said to be in the most miserable plight, and when they joined the troops at Fort George to resemble a moving hospital rather than a corps of efficient men." Requests information concerning opinions from Albany on the Montreal expedition and laments the death of [Jean Victor Marie] Moreau.
  - 1813 November 23. David Breasley ALS to John Armstrong; Camp F[ort] Mills., 2 pages; Discusses the conduct of his regiment's paymaster and recommends "the Appointment of Second Lieut. Daniel Bunch as P. Master of the 15th Regiment."
  - 1813 November 24. Ferdinand Leigh Claiborne DS to John T. Wirt; Fort Claiborne, [Alabama]., 2 pages; Regarding payment for articles purchased as presents to the "Indian Chief Pushmatahaw [Pushmataha] & other of his Warriors" by the order of Brigadier General Claiborne. Includes the acknowledged receipt of $113.82 and "three-fourths in full of the above account."
  - 1813 November 29. John M. Garnett ALS to Archibald R. S. Hunter; Loretto, [Virginia]., 3 pages; Mentions the blockade; "We are…closely blockaded by his Satanic majesty's ships and unable to sell a bushel of corn or wheat." Expresses outrage at non-patriotism of pacifists; "men [who] are lost to every feeling of patriotism and sense of duty to their country - men who are avowed apologists of every crime and outrage perpetrated against us..."
  - 1813 December 4. Abraham Shoemaker, Jr. ALS to Charles Thomson; Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania]., 2 pages; Regarding rent payments; "The young gentleman in whose favor, at my request, you signed a recommendation for a commission in the army received a lieutenancy and serves in that capacity at Fort George, N.C. He has been promoted to a Captaincy in the 15 Reg. U.S. Inf.y and is now attached to Genl. Wilkinson's Army on the frontier of Canada."
  - 1813 December 8. Maskline Clark partially printed document to William Simmons; [Dover, Delaware]., 1 page; "The United States in account current with Lieut. Maskline Clark Jr. of the 32d Regiment U.S. Infantry."Lists expenses of Lieutenant Clark of the 32nd Regiment, U.S. Infantry."Cash paid for contingencies," including drummers, men to play the fife, prison fees for deserters, and housing. Also, expenses incurred for wood, straw, and repairs to the barracks.
  - 1813 December 20. Stephen Decatur LS to William Jones; U.S. Ship United States, New London, [Connecticut]., 4 pages; Trapped in the harbor by British ships, Decatur decribes the actions of Nathaniel Seuter, a lawyer and captain in the 25th Regiment of the Rhode Island Infantry, visiting the British ships; "He admitted without hesitation, that he intended to go on board the blockading ships for the purpose of taking is wife to see them."
  - 1813 December 20. George Murray ALS to Return Jonathan Meigs., 1 page; Petition to cancel fine levied upon him for not serving in Militia, "by reson of my sore affliction at that time…I had a very soreness and [pang] in my brest and lung…[I] hope that you will have compassion..."
  - 1813 December 20. Alexander Neef ALS to Andrew W. Bell; Plattsburg, [New York]., 6 pages; Eyewitness account of the Battle of Chateaugay.
  - 1813 December 21. William Groves ALS to William Carner; Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania]., 1 page; Description of Philadelphia meeting where it was voted to dump tea overboard to protest American war-time profiteering; "Upwards of 500 people Attended And they...agread to do with out Sugar Tea & Coffe...Before we Ajurned one moved that the Tea be thrown over Board witch was Carried Unanimes…our men are going well at the Suthard they have gained Anothe victory over the ingins killd 250...Good news Just Arrived there is An embarg Laid."
  - 1813 December 24. William Reed ALS; Washington, [D.C.]., 2 pages; Regarding Madison’s administration; "We have not the slightest estimation of a change of Temper in the Administration - or…from any quarter. A gloomy stupidity seems to pervade them on every question of general policy. no business of importance has been undertaken in either house since the passage of this suicidal Embargo - The Absence of the Secy of War checks any efforts for correcting or improving that Department."
  - 1813 December 25 to 1814 January 3. United States Army. 5 Manuscripts., 5 pages; Regarding payment for use of the Mohawk and Seneca Turnpike and passage over the Cayuga Bridge.
  - [1813]. John McNiel, Jr. Cy to Francis Cogswell., 1 page; Regarding military accounts and infantry regiment recruitment; "officers on the recruiting service must be…careful not to enlist…disordered persons…"
  - [1813]. Zenas Stebbins ALS to John T. Apthorp., 2 pages; Requesting pay; "Please to pay…the money that is dew to me for transporting my Pieces to [Amherst]…" Includes list of 59 soldiers in Stebbins' company of Massachusetts Artillery.
  - 1813. 10 Manuscripts., 13 pages; Receipts, etc.
  - 1813. 4 Manuscripts., 6 pages; Accounts.
  - 1813. 15 Manuscripts., 15 pages; Receipts.
  - 1814 January 8. Joseph Wiggin ALS to James Monroe; New York, [New York]., 3 pages; Regarding the attempt to obtain a passport; "I came to this City from Barton for to embark…for England, being informed that Govt would not be very - particular, in giving passports, under circumstances which had no connection with political events, and where necessity required the same."
  - 1814 January 12. Rawstorne Wilson and Wilson ALS to Rowson and Son; Preston., 1 page; Regarding supply vacancies in the local militia.
  - 1814 January 17. S[amuel] T. A[nderson] ALS to [Selina Anderson]; Schenectady, [New York]., 2 pages; Unhappy being away from home, "but afraid to return unless I can tell the Sec[retar]y of the Navy that the business he sent me upon, is freely and properly executed." Recent snowfall enables them to retrieve "guns and heavy articles" from Rhinebeck. Still awaiting orders from Commodore [Isaac] Chauncey (1772-1840), "about cordage to be made at Albany." "My wish- anxiety- desire- to see you is greater than I can tell you." Made the acquaintance of a Frenchman, De Launay, "a near connexion of the Gentleman of that name who was governor of the Bastile." Notes De Launay's dislike of the Bonaparte government and his emigration to America to escape it. "Buonaparte according to his opinion, draws near the close of his tyrannical career, and Europe to the end of her miseries." Will try to get more evidence concerning his title to his grandfather's property in Scotland.
  - 1814 January 18. Samuel Tupper ALS to Augustus Porter; Le Roy., 3 pages; Describes the burning of the city he was in; "I send you few Papers enclosed herewith which are all that I saved from the flames…I arrived at Buffaloe four daus before it was burnt with all my Papers Packed…"
  - 1814 January 19. Philip Mathewson ALS to Jeffery Mathewson; Hamilton, [New York]., 3 pages; Discusses movement of local militia, describes sickness in the community, prices for food; "our militia here have been called out this fall Destined for Sackets harbour & ware marched to Brown Ville ten miles this side the harbour…"; Original located in the Mathewson family papers.
  - 1814 January 25. William Jones LS to Thomas Manning and James Shapley; Treasury Department [Washington, D.C.]., 3 pages; Concerning the bounty of 21 prisoners captured and brought in by the vessel Fox, "as allowed by the act of the 2d of August last. It is considered that this bounty is not payable except upon prisoners as well captured, as brought in and delivered over, after the date of the act." Requests proof that the capture was made after August 2nd, and evidence of their being authorized to receive the money "in behalf of the owners, officers, and crew of the Fox when it will be paid."
  - 1814 January 30. Benjamin Polk DS; Fort Strother [Alabama]., 1 page; Account regarding 3 muskets; accepted by Polk on October 26, 1816.
  - 1814 February 3. Gordon Drummond DS. Kingston, [Canada]., 10 pages; Proceedings of the Court Martial of Israel Elsworth for deserting the 2nd Regiment Leed’s Militia. Lists the members of the Court Martial. Includes Elsworth’s testimony describing his settlement in Canada, his draft into the militia, and efforts by Doctor Schofield to acquire his farm. Schofield stated he held a commission in the militia and had authority, that "the people of the States would overcome the British Government in Upper Canada," and thus Elsworth could return to the United States. Signed by Edward Walker and John Ferguson, Judge and President of the Court Martial. Approved and signed by Gordon Drummond.
  - 1814 February 6. Henry Burbeck ALS to Constant Freeman; New London, [Connecticut]., 1 page; Drawing rations; "Will you inform me whether General [Thomas] Cushing draws double rations for the command of the District, or the Commanding Officer of Fort Independence and wether he [signs] a Certificate on his subsistance Account to this effect." Burbeck certifies that he was the commanding officer at Independence and that the pay master has a certificate to that effect.
  - 1814 February 11. Thomas Tingey LS to James Beatty; Navy Yard, Washington [D.C.]., 1 page; Refers to items for John Cannon for two sloops; enclosed are Cannon's receipt for "Sundry articles forwarded by his Waggons for the two sloops…The boxes & Barrels being Masked with their contints." He will write two captains designating what is intended for each.
  - 1814 February 13. James Wilkinson LS to Thomas A. Smith; Camp French Mills [Covington, New York]., 2 pages; Plan to attack Prescot and Kingston, encloses an order regarding a change of command, and congratulates Smith on his promotion. "You are to understand that all the movement in and from this quarter have been directed by the Secretary of War, at the very time I had nearly completed my arrangements to Storm Prescot and attack Kingston."
  - 1814 February 14. [Ragan V. Radis?] ALS to William Rhinelander & Co., 1 page; Sugar market is doing poorly. "Our Sugar Refiners have generally stopt working." Notes prices for loaf sugar, lump sugar, and molasses. Hopeful that molasses may have better sales soon, but "as our market so much depends on our political affairs makes it impossible for us to say what it may be in the spring."
  - 1814 February 18. John Todd ALS to Francis Catterson., 2 pages; Request for money; "I stand in Need of a few Dolars I wish you to Send to me Eight or ten by James and Charge it to my account…" Includes receipt on back signed by James Todd stating that ten dollars was received.
  - 1814 February 21. William Onderdonk, Jr. ALS to Henry F. Jones; New York., 3 pages; Bill for a schooner and news of its capture; "You will receive enclosed the bill…for Schooner Attach & cargo amounting to $255…I am very much mortified to inform you of the capture of this Schooner, & what renders it the more mortifying, is, that she was taken up the river Mississippi 12 miles above the bar & after she had passed Fort Charles, from which one Shabby General Flournoy thought it expedient to withdraw his men, which gave the enemy an undisturbed possession of the river..."
  - 1814 March 5. Alexander Stewart ALS to Sir Phineas Riall; Fourteen Mile Creek [Indiana]., 2 pages; Intelligence of a British military defeat [the Battle of Longwoods]; "I regret that our Loss is very considerable." Mentions [William] Caldwell's Rangers and dealings with Native Americans.